<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:date>2020-08-29</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The visit of the Mantis to the houses of the Ticks, who, excepting one boy, have hidden themselves away in the fleeces of their sheep. Evil thoughts of the Mantis with regard to this boy, who is left in charge of the pots of food which are upon the fire. The return of the Ticks, their attack upon the Mantis, his flight home, his revenge upon the Ticks for their inhospitality and ill-treatment of him, the consequent destitution of the Ticks, which is lamented by the relatives of the Mantis, the monster //khwai-hemm is now, by the wish of the Mantis, unwillingly summoned by his daughter, the Porcupine, to swallow for them a portion of the Ticks flock of sheep, his fearful appearance and unlimited voracity...... he swallows the Mantis, and the brave |kwammana as well, the fiery trial of the young sons of the Mantis and |kwammana by the Porcupine, the monster ||khwai-hemm slain, the re-appearance of all the animals and things which had just been swallowed by him, the removal of the survivors from the place where he lay dead (L II.-32. 2916-2965, 33. 2966-3057, 34. 3058-3149). The monster //khwai-hemms speech to the Mantis and the reply of the latter are given separately (B XXIII. 2161-2210, 2234-2247). After fleeing the Ticks, |kaggen (the Mantis) goes to sleep and dreams that he takes away all the Tick's things while they sleep. He and the Ichneumon wake up and see that the Tick's things and sheep have been taken and are at |kaggen's house. |kaggen goes on to say how he and his family will behave in the future. |kaggen asks the Porcupine to fetch her father who devours things.</dc:description>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/293</dc:identifier>
  <dc:title>The Mantis takes away the Tick's sheep (including Porcupine's speech concerning the coming of ||khwai-hemm)</dc:title>
</oai_dc:dc>
