<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>Dorothea Bleek</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-12</dc:date>
  <dc:description>Notes on rock paintings in caves in the Orange Free State c.1928, including comments on condition of the paintings, location of the caves and comparision between Stow's copies and originals. Also some fragments of stories and some words. 1) p. [1] Groendraai. 43.97? Location of cave, figures and bucks (possibly eland), description of cave, finding the cave and location of farm. 2) p.1-10 [3-13]: Theunissen Skoolplaas (Mr Prinsloo and Martin Louw) |kesiy. Personal history and sentences, some genealogy. 3) p. [14] 'p 107. 128' Glen on Beersheba, Mrs van der Merwe's farm, location of cave, description of condition of drawings (much spoilt), colours, Basotho shields, reference to Orpen having cut out lots and sent them away, some to Bloemfontein, about the farm. 4) p. [17] notes on people who might know about Bushmen paintings. 5) p. [18] Location of cave sites, brief description of painting, figures and a 'dead' animal. 6) Rest of the book is blank except for the last 11 pages at the back 7) p. [19, first from back of book] Place names and numbers, verso page mentions Orpen 1876, opposite page features a to-do list. 8) p. [21] 78.105.116 (117) Location of cave on van Niekerk's Rust, owners name, history of farm, poor condition of cave and paintings, smears and parts rubbed out, comparison with Stow copies, high up paintings clearer, figures and eland, 117 could not be identified. 9) p. [24]: locations of farms and caves and lattitudes. 10) p. [25] Cambridge addresses. 11) p. [26-27] untranslated script possibly seSotho. 12) p.[27v] Story of the man and his son. 13) p. [28] The holy cat. 14) p. [28v] The thief and the shoe. 15) p.[29] fragment of 'a rope and a stone' 16) p.[29v] An untitled story fragment..</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/2048</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publishers>Dorothea Bleek</dc:publishers>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Dorothea Bleek</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Dorothea Bleek notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>Dorothea Bleek - Book BC151_A3_024</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
