<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>||kam||ari, Kabala, ||k'abe, ||klon|ki, |ke|ke, To'be, Tata'basa, =hobeku, ||kobe, =nobuke, ||ko:ve</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-06</dc:date>
  <dc:description>Notes on |auni Vol.2, made at Frankenwald Research Station, Witwatersrand University (presumably, it doesn't say so in the notebook). Words and sentences and personal history, including some rough genealogies. Also some fragmented information relating to daily life including hunting, taking a wife, making huts, 'curing', and artefacts, as well as the 'retirement' of menstruating girls in huts. The final unnumbered pages of the notebook have been left blank. 1) Written on opposite page of inside front cover '|auni II'. 2) p.468: 20.10.36. ||k'abe and his wife |kam|ari. Words and sentences including a description of the village and some personal history [coming from/through Kuruman]. 3) [p.473 crossed out]: Diagram of village layout with numbers and names. 4) p.473-475: |kalakap? Personal history and genealogical diagrams. 5) p.475: 21.10.36. =nobuke. Personal history, and words and sentences including receptacles for fetching water: 'The Kalahari has no pots, no buckets, no dishes, no mug, no plate.' 6) p.482: 22.10.36. |kam|ari and ||klon|ki and |ke|ke. Words and sentences including personal history, lots about the seasons and food, genealogies. 7) p.487: 23.10.36. Vaalpens [place?]. ||kam||ari and Kabala. Personal history and words and sentences, languages spoken. 8) p496: 24.10.36. To'be, Tata'basa and Kabala. Words and sentences including the naming of children, oxen and a wagon, ornaments and dress worn by women, some personal history. 9) p.502: 26.10.36. =hobeku and ||kobe. Sentences relating to daily life including going out to collect food and returning, doctors who come to the hut to anoint and cure illness, they come to make cuts and rub, but have no medicine [p.505], shooting and cutting up meat, carrying it in the bag and cooking it at home. 10) p.509-514. 27.10.36. ||klon|ki. The girl in her hut getting her period, what she does in the hut 'go into retirement' the young people dance for her, her granny cuts her, personal history and language spoken, making a sieve, genealogy. 11) p.515: 28.10.36. ||kobe. Rain, water and lightening, huts built, tasks performed by men and woman including thatching, some personal history mostly involving dead children, springtime and the arrival of plants and berries, eating, 'knocking over' a jackal and a red cat. 12) p.521: 29.10.36. ||ko:ve. Sentences about living in huts, working jackal skin, being beaten at work, bad people, 'marriage still nominally by capture,' lots of personal history, a description of a man taking a woman [p.527]. 13) p.529: 30.10.36. ||ko:ve. Sentences, wagon, water and huts, throwing a stick, methods of carrying (on the head). 14) p.537: 28.05.97 [sic] ||kabe and |kam||ari, words and sentences, reference to a motor car, personal history and the death of people (Old Abraham for eg) and their children at Johannesburg and Tweerivier..</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/2054</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Dorothea Bleek notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>Dorothea Bleek - Book BC151_A3_030</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
