<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:contributor>The New Digital Bleek and Lloyd Archive</dc:contributor>
  <dc:creator>Masarwa</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-20</dc:date>
  <dc:description>Notebook. Notes and words, Masarwa. 1) p.144: Masarwa. Thursday July 17th 1913; 2) p.159: 18th July; 3) p.173: Saturday 19th July; 4) p.181: Sunday 20th July; 5) p.199: Monday 21st July; 6) p.200: on the eating and other habits of men and women, 7) p.201: contnd, 'The men make all the bread', a bread recipe; 8) p.205: Tues 22nd; 9) p.211: Wednesday 23 July; 10) p.219: Thursday 24th July; 11) p.223: Sunday 27th July; 12) p.234: Tuesday 29th: Summary of a fable related by Madjonka [?] in Setshuana to Ampisletsi [?] retold in English by the latter -  concerning a woman who cannot have children and some birds who promise to tell her things in exchange for seeds, her husband is told to kill an ox, the insides become girl children. The girls are told not to leave the house but do not listen. A man at a waterwell falls in love with one of the girls, they disappear into dust. The man asks the woman for the girls and she produces them one by one. The man takes the girl and her servant away and their identities become confused. The story ends with the people tricking the false wife into climbing into a hole they have dug, and covering her up, killing her; 13) p.239: Wednesday 30th; 14) p.243-248: A Setshuana story related by the same narrator was told to him by his uncle's wife, a Bakalahari woman. It concerns a man who wants to marry his daughter but she refuses. He wants to make her a servant for refusing. Her sister says she will show her an escape. She meets many people along the way and tells them her story. The people tell the chief, a snake, about her and she marries him. Her family go to her as there is hunger at their old place, and the husband wants to give them a sheep and a goat to eat but his wife refuses saying she has no parents, giving the sister thick milk instead. The sister remains behind and the parents return to their place. The younger sister kills her sister's husband because she feels he is a snake. She puts his bones in the gound with water, beats the ground with a stick, and he comes out as a person and everyone is pleased. ; 15) pp.258-277 are blank..</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/2032</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Dorothea Bleek</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Dorothea Bleek</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Dorothea Bleek notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>Dorothea Bleek - Book BC151_A3_008</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
