<item type="story"><id>374</id>
<collection>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</collection>
<title>The Rain&apos;s story, and |kannu the waterhole</title>
<summary><i>A note has been made, from //kábbo’s information, of a story not yet written down in Bushman, telling how the Rain carried off a girl belonging to the First Bushmen (or the ancient people living before the Bushmen), who afterwards became a frog, her kaross being changed into a springbok, etc. Her people were also transformed (L II.-37. 3335 rev. and 3336 rev.). Versions of this transformation into frogs, ascribed chiefly to a New Maiden’s acts of disobedience, are given in the Katkop dialect by !kwéiten ta ||kên (L VI.-1. 3930-3958), and by Dia!kwãin (B XXVII. 2609-2618, continued in L V.-2. 3864-3881).</i> Three maidens get caught in the rain. Two of the older girls glide across the Rain&apos;s back safely, but the third girl is a new maiden and falls into the spring and becomes a frog. The water-hole&apos;s name is |kannu.</summary><comments>1) The page numbers in this book (VI-1) are duplicates of those in notebook IV-4, 2) The story<i> |kannu the waterhole</i> appears on a separate page (p.3941) but is related to the rest of this story so has been included here, 3) p.3929v: This story was told to !kweiten ta ||ken by her mother (≠kamme-an), 4) p.3930v: frogs are people the rain has put into the spring (called <i>xhwarra</i>), 5) See also <i>The maiden&apos;s story; the frog&apos;s story </i>and<i> A yet unwritten story, about the Rain and one of the First Bushmen girls carried away by a whirlwind and who became a frog </i>and<i> About new maidens</i>, 6) This story is found in Book VI-1</comments><date>19 – 20 December 1874</date><storypages>3930-3941 </storypages><category>New maidens</category><category>The Rain and Rain&apos;s water</category><author>!kweiten ta ||ken (Rachel) (VI)</author>
<page><file>A2_1_50_03930.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_050</book></page>
<page><file>A2_1_50_03931.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_050</book></page>
<page><file>A2_1_50_03932.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_050</book></page>
<page><file>A2_1_50_03933.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_050</book></page>
<page><file>A2_1_50_03934.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_050</book></page>
<page><file>A2_1_50_03935.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_050</book></page>
<page><file>A2_1_50_03936.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_050</book></page>
<page><file>A2_1_50_03937.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_050</book></page>
<page><file>A2_1_50_03938.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_050</book></page>
<page><file>A2_1_50_03939.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_050</book></page>
<page><file>A2_1_50_03940.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_050</book></page>
<page><file>A2_1_50_03941.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_050</book></page>
</item>
