<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:contributor>The New Digital Bleek and Lloyd Archive</dc:contributor>
  <dc:creator>Dia!kwain (David Hoesar) (V)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-10-05</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The power over ostriches possessed by /uherre (maternal uncle of Dia!kwain). This is followed by a long discourse concerning successful and unsuccessful hunting, as well as by a prayer, addressed by the mother of the narrator to the dead, that her husbands hunting might prove more fortunate. The result of this prayer is described. Allusion is also made to the belief that unsuccessful hunting may forebode danger to the hunter. In the Katkop dialect, by Dia!kwain (L V.-10. 4778-4795-4868). Dia!kwain's uncle |uherre had in the past asked his spirit ancestors to give the people bad luck with the game because they had abused him. A man says that |uherre made an ostrich come to him, but complains that it is a lean bird. An old woman warns him that magicians first send lean, old and ugly things to test them. The people must eat the lean ostrich, after which fat ones will be sent to them. Dia!kwain's mother (and other women) beat the digging stone on the ground to pray to the spirit-people. The story moves on to a more general narrative about game-sorcerers and spirit-people. 1) p.4777v: |uherre's 'little' name was |kai kwa (see also Why Dia!kwain's uncle |kai kwa received his name); he could not speak Dutch and was Dia!kwain's mother's brother, 2) p.4788v describes the dwarf ostrich (!kaui-!kwa) and accounts for its growth; it is usually a female which comes from an 'outer' egg (which the old people say does not belong to the mother), 3) pp.4801v-4809v: see |nu-!ke or magicians who have died still possess power, and =kamme-an's prayer to them, 4) p.4810v: Lloyd compares the 'spirit people' or |nu- !k'e with those of other races; a pasted-in insert from Public Opinion (June 1875) regarding the 'Iwis' from 'Nicobar Land' who are spirits of the deceased, or demons, 5) p.4811v: the people pray to the spirit-people by beating the ground, 6) pp.4815v &amp; 4816v: the spirit-people turn their backs; if they turn around they become aware of what is happening to the people, 7) p.4823v: the |xam name of the ostrich egg-white and egg-yolk), 8) p.4850v: the name of Dia!kwain's maternal grandmother; about killing things that 'travel' (often while wounded) and killing things that lie 'stretched out': the latter bring misfortune to the hunter if they are killed, 9) p.4855v: Dia!kwain's maternal grandfather's 'little' name (he cannot remember his 'great' name), 10) This story is found in Books V-10 and V-11.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/442</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The power over ostriches possessed by Dia!kwain's uncle, |uherre or 'Blaitje'</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
