<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>Dia!kwain (David Hoesar) (V)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-14</dc:date>
  <dc:description>A full-grown Bushman, whom the narrator knew, punished by a lion for having eaten forbidden portions of the lions prey, as a child. Told by Dia!kwain (L V.-8. 4574-4617 1/2,  9. 4618, with notes upon 4616 rev. and 4617 rev.). |xam parents tell their children about what happened to Xwerri-kau, as a lesson about the eating of certain things: Xwerri-kau (who had eaten prohibited parts of game as a child) was pursuing a quagga when a lion sprang on him, and the quagga lay down to die once it saw that the lion had bitten him. This story illustrates how lions remember what children do and take revenge in various ways on the hunting ground when they are grown-ups. It also contains information about the hunting-ground. 1) p.4577v: Xwerri-kau's father had shot the quagga with 'Boomgift' (!gau u ken) and still it ran as if not wounded; Xwerri-kau's Dutch name was Jantje, but after this incident he was known by them as 'Oud Jantje Leeuw Stert', or Old Jantje Lion Tail, 2) p.4583v: the |xam name (!nau) for a thing that 'obstinately' goes where it wants to go, 3) p.4588v: Brand Vlei, on the side of the Zak River where the quagga ran, and the bush called xanna where the lion was, 4) p.4593v: it seems Xwerri-kau escaped from the lion (he kicked it in the testicles) making it 'ashamed', 5) p.4610v: |xam terms for the breaking of bones (!kwa !kwak-ka) and the breaking of flesh (!kwa !kwabba-ka), 5) 4615v: (Dia!kwain, 26 April) terms for the pouring of liquid into things, 6) pp.4616v &amp; 4617v: see The lion's dream: the lion has the ability to make things obey its will; the people do not understand the lion's actions because it is a beast of prey, 8) p.4618 opp: a note on |xam terms used for driving things: wild game (||gamma-sse) and tame things (sswai), 9) See also The children taught to use another name for the lion, 10) This story is found in Books V-8 and V-9.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/424</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>What the lion did to Xwerri-kau; and what parts of game should not be eaten by little children</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
