<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:contributor>The New Digital Bleek and Lloyd Archive</dc:contributor>
  <dc:creator>||kabbo (Jantje) (II)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-10-05</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The Jackal and the Hyena' (in which piece there are interminable speeches by the Jackal) contains many allusions to other fables, and really forms part of the lengthy discourse of the Dawns-Heart, (L II.-19. 1710-1759, 20. 1760-1855, 21. 1856-1948). The foolish Jackals fight among themselves and the Hyena takes away their prey. A Jackal scolds and lectures the others and they then hunt, drink water and discuss their own doings and the doings of the Hyena. Other animals are discussed, such as the ||kaitchi, the |gipp (Proteles), the wild dog, the lynx, the cat, the lion, the old hyena and the doings of the hunter and his dog. 1) This story is a part of the discourses of the Day's Heart star, 2) 'Dreaming' as used in this story seems to mean 'thinking' or the 'talking of thoughts', 3) Date on p.1927: 21 August, 4) p.1793v: someone who keeps springbok to eat alone is called 'hyena' (or !gwai) by his fellows, 5) p.1834v: the markings of the present-day hyena, 6) p.1844v: people lay kaross skins on top of old beds, which hyenas eat, 7) p.1909v: a note on the lynx's 'doubling' behaviour, 8) See also The Day's Heart star and The doings of the jackals, 9) This story is found in Books II-20 and II-21.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/266</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The Jackal's speech, or, the Jackals and a springbok which the Hyena takes away from them</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
