<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>|han=kass'o (Klein Jantje) (VIII)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-02 17:22:27.859034</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The !khau (a lizard of the genus Agama) and his daughter, the Mice, and the Mantis. By /han=kasso (L VIII.30. 8671-8702, 31. 8703-8736). The !khau (Agama lizard) tricks a series of Long-nosed Mice, hitting them on the head with a stick and taking their springbok to feed his daughter. |kaggen (the Mantis) dreams that the !khau is killing the Mice and tells the Striped Mouse. The Striped Mouse goes and hunts near to where the other Mice had been hunting. The !khau calls over the Striped Mouse, who tricks him in the same way that the !khau had tricked the other mice, and sets his companions free by killing the !khau. 1) p.8672v: translated by Dorothea Bleek from August 1919, 2) p.8670v: |han=kass'o heard this from his maternal grandmother (=kammi); the !khau is a lizard of the genus Agama, 3) pp.8671 and 8672: the song of the Agama lizard, 4) p.8681v: on the term meaning 'hill's man', 5) p.8708v: words and sentences, 6) p.8727v: making different clicks (lateral, cerebral, palatal and dental), 7) p.8728v: names for and descriptions of flowers and stones, 8) See also The Wildebeest, the Mice, the Quaggas and the Mantis, or why the (black) Wildebeest has a white or light coloured tail and The Mantis, the Mice and the Beetle, 9) This story is found in Books VIII-30 and VIII-31.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/906</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The Lizard, the Mice and the Mantis (includes the song of the Agama lizard)</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
