<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>||kabbo (Jantje) (II)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-01</dc:date>
  <dc:description>An account of what the Anteater says various animals should eat, who they should marry, where they live, and what they look and smell like and why. This story is from the Early Times when people were animals. The animals all assent to what the Anteater says. ...The Anteater then lays down the law with regard to the proper food for different animals, and that their marriages should be suitable.  They all listen to the Anteater, and also to the Lynx, who repeats to them the Anteaters words... she [the Anteater] again proceeds to deliver to the Lynx her important messages concerning the nature and habits of the different animals. 1) pp.415-421 were translated with Dia!kwain's assistance on 5 March 1875, 2) Date on p.421: 11 August; p.445: 13 August; p.447: 25 August; p.467: 8 November, 3) p.416v: the pau bird (=ko a) is described as a large bird with white neck and breast and a black back, which eats locusts, 3) p.420v: Dia!kwain (5 March 1875) notes the similarity between these stories told by ||kabbo and those his own mother told him. She was from the same part of the country as ||kabbo and was related to him. He also gives the genealogy and the names of mutual relations, 4) p.427v: descriptions of animals (especially snakes), 5) p.468v: a note by ||kabbo on a thorn tree's flowers which are pretty, large and white and blow in the wind, 6) p.470v: notes by ||kabbo describing various animals (especially types of mice), 7) See also The Anteater, Springbok and Lynx (||kabbo's version 1) and The Anteater's story or The Anteater, Springbok, Lynx and Partridge and The Anteater, Springbok and Lynx (//kabbo's version 2) and The Korhaan marries his elder sister (the Anteater's laws) (//kabbo's version 2), 8) This story is found in Book II-3.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/198</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The Anteater's laws (||kabbo's version 2)</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
