<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>Tamme (XII)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-06</dc:date>
  <dc:description>U'we (or |xue) creates things (including food animals). The Moon says that the people shall return again from death (and not die outright). The Moon tells the Hare that the Hare's dead son will return to life, but the Hare objects, saying that his dead son smells bad. |xue laughs at the Hare and beats him. The Moon tells |xue to leave the Hare alone, but |xue ignores the Moon. The Hare's wife beats |xue. The Moon tells the She-Hare to leave |xue alone, but she tells the Moon that she will kill |xue for beating her husband. The male Hare gets up and kills |xue, who does not die outright. The Moon kills |xue a number of times, but he does not die outright. The Moon and his wife threaten each other. The Moon's wife tells the Moon to kill |xue, but the Moon is afraid. 1) This story is continued and concluded in Book XI-1: see End of Moon and Hare story (!nanni), 2) p.9626v: Tamme heard this from his paternal grandfather (Nakka), 3) p.9650v: D. Bleek began translating at this point (on the page opposite) in 1924, 4) p.9655v: (20 November 1880) the !kun names of animals found in the boys' country, 5) The |xam narratives contain many similar tales concerning the creation of death (see also The Moon and the little Hare in |xam Book II-6 and Story of the Moon and the Hare: a version at first by =kasin and then by Dia!kwain in |xam Book IV-4), 6) This story is found in Book XI &amp; XII-8.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/1057</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd !kun notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The Moon and the Hare and |xue</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
