<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>||kabbo (Jantje) (II)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-12</dc:date>
  <dc:description>Bushman Presentiments. They feel in their bodies that certain events are going to happen. There is a kind of beating of the flesh, which tells them things. Those who are stupid do not understand these teachings; they disobey them, and get into trouble, such as being killed by a lion, etc. The beatings tell those who understand them, which way they are not to go, and which arrow they had better not use, and also warn them when many people are coming to the house on a wagon. They inform people where they can find the person of whom they are in search, i.e., which way they must go to seek him successfully (LII.-28. 2531-2565). The |xam believe that dreams deceive people whereas presentiments speak the truth. The narrator taps his blood when he is about to kill springbok and the people feel tapping while they sit waiting for the ostriches to come. The verso pages contain additional details about the /kumm or 'Bushman letters'. 1) p.2530v: 'Bushman letters' are compared with letters that carry messages to another place, 2) p.2531v: these beatings, or 'Bushman letters', are called !gwe, 3) p.2536v: two |xam names for Brinkkop and a description, 4) p.2541v: ||kabbo says that |kaggen named all places, but not the people, 5) p.2542v: a name of the thorn tree's flower, 6) p.2551v: the ostrich can see with its eye's bones, which function as a bony cylinder through which they see, 7) p.2554v: the springbok's markings influence where the tappings occur, 8) p.2556v: a comparison between letting the game get away and an anecdote about missing the train, 9) p.2563v: a note by Lloyd on her delay of a week in taking down narration due to Bleek's holiday, and her and ||kabbo's poor health, 10) This story is found in Book II-28.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/287</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publishers>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publishers>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The Bushmen's presentiments of things that are going to happen</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
