<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>!nanni (XI)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-06</dc:date>
  <dc:description>|xue bites his father, breaking his father's finger. |xue's father goes away. |xue  becomes a shana (the fruit of a small tree). The rain falls on him, and he lies down and cries when the rain is over. His father hears him and throws him over his shoulder. |xue cries very loudly so his father puts him down and he follows his father. |xue grabs a little |ou (a little buck, probably a steenbok) from some birds (!kuara). |xue's father roasts some of the meat and leaves for his own country. |xue sits at the fire and cries for his father to carry him. |xue hears his father's laughing and gets up, crying. He becomes rain and tells the rain to pour down on his father. |xue's father beats |xue and tells his wife to give |xue to another person so they can kill him. |xue hears this and cries and his father leaves. |xue follows his father and at sunrise he becomes !naxane. |xue's father puts two of the !naxane into his bag. |xue changes back to |xue and |xue's father searches for the !naxane. |xue climbs a !gua tree and refuses to come down, being afraid of being beaten. |xue's mother slaps him so that he falls from the tree. |xue becomes a lizard (gora) and then a bird (called ||kanna-tatta). [It says 'to be continued' on page 9489v, but it is not clear where the story is taken up.] 1) p.9436v: !nanni heard this from his paternal grandfather (Karu); the names of different dress (front-dress and tails); the names for noises made by beating different parts of the body with a knobkerrie, 2) p.9442v: (6 May 1880) the names of dress worn by men and women (short skin apron, long apron, woman's front dress, male's front dress), 3) p.9446v: names for tinder and tinderbox used by the !kun and the Ovaherero; 4) pp.9458v-9468v: see !nanni's uncle, 5) p.9460v: the Biriko yau are people who live near the Makoba, 6) p.9472v: names for the times of day, 7) p.9488v: a note about the names of sticks: this relates to !nanni's drawing of 15 June 1880 (see NLLB_D_!n044); !nanni's father's name, 8) This story is found in Book XI &amp; XII-6.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/1039</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd !kun notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>|xue and his father</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
