<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>!kweiten ta ||ken (Rachel) (VI)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-12</dc:date>
  <dc:description>A note has been made, from //kabbos information, of a story not yet written down in Bushman, telling how the Rain carried off a girl belonging to the First Bushmen (or the ancient people living before the Bushmen), who afterwards became a frog, her kaross being changed into a springbok, etc. Her people were also transformed (L II.-37. 3335 rev. and 3336 rev.). Versions of this transformation into frogs, ascribed chiefly to a New Maidens acts of disobedience, are given in the Katkop dialect by !kweiten ta //ken (L VI.-1. 3930-3958), and by Dia!kwain (B XXVII. 2609-2618, continued in L V.-2. 3864-3881). A maiden is secluded (in a house of illness) and she goes out and kills and eats the Water's children. The maiden's mother goes to the Water's spring where rain-clouds come out and a whirlwind carries the spring away. The whirlwind carries away the maiden and her whole family and they become frogs. Their things such as their arrows also went into the spring and later grew by the side of it. 1) The page numbers in this book (VI-1) are duplicates of those in notebook IV-4, 2) Date on p.3949: 21 December, 3) p.3941v: this story was told to !kweiten ta ||ken by her mother (=kamme-an); !kweiten ta ||ken has not seen the Water's children, but has heard descriptions of them; they are the children of 'great things', such as rainbulls and raincows, 4) p.3957v: all the things that grow by the xhwarra belonged to the First Bushmen, or !khwe |na sse !ke; the use and manufacture of |xam in the building of houses, 5) See also A yet unwritten story, about the Rain and one of the First Bushmen girls carried away by a whirlwind and who became a frog and About new maidens (continued from Bleek's Book XXVII: p.2618) and The Rain's story, and |kannu the waterhole and About new maidens, 6) This story is found in Book VI-1.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/375</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The maiden's story; the frog's story</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
