<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>Griet; Cela; Piet Lynx (I; II; III)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-11</dc:date>
  <dc:description>Thirty pages of interviews collected by Jemima Bleek in 1879 with a three 'Hottentot' informants (I, II and III), members of a family ('Lynx') sent to the house in Mowbray in error. The vocabulary mostly concerns parts of the human body, features of the landscape and daily life, and names of animals, and there are some sentences and phrases (most of which were given by 'Piet') concerning times of the day and daily life. There are also snippets of personal history and many examples of communication in Dutch in the course of the interviews. 1) The front cover of the notebook reads "Hottentot. Pp. 1-30. 1879. I. II. &amp; III. - 1. Collected by J.C. Bleek."; 2) Inside the front cover it reads "From 27th January 1879 To 2nd July 1879."; 3) There are three blank pages in the front of this section of the notebook; 4) p.1: 27th January 1879, 'Griet' (or 'G'), contributions on the opposite page appear to have been made by 'Cela' (or 'C') the next day (28/1/79); 5) p.4: 'Cela' is the contributor; 6) p.5: 31/1/79; 7) p.5v: 'Piet' contributes on the 4/2/79, with 'Cela' continuing on p.6; 8) p.10: 11/2/79. Piet Lynx. There is much Dutch recorded on these pages; 9) p.10v: John Lynx, Piet's eldest brother lives on Doorn's [?] fontein, he has one child left [?] and a young wife. An individual [?] called Darnster is from Sandtdrift and has two children; 10) p.11 features translations largely in Dutch; 11) p.12: "P.L. 12/3/79" and lower down the page 7/4/79; 12) p.13v features contributions by 'Jantje', with Piet's contributions on p.14; 13) p.16: 10/4/79 and 11/4/79; 14) p.17: 14/4/79; 15) p.19: 'P.' 20/6/79; 16) p.21: Piet. 24/6/79; 17) p.23: 25/6/79, 'P.L'; 18) p.28: 'P.L.' 2/7/79; 19) p.28v: 'This and the following page gone over with Piet Lynx 12 January /80'; 20) pages 31 onwards are blank and unnumbered; 21) This collection is found in the one half of a notebook of interviews conducted by Jemima Bleek. The other half of the notebook contains interviews with two !kun contributors, !nanni and Tamme, and has a different cover; 22) This half of the notebook is numbered I. II. &amp; III. -1..</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/2024</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Jemima Bleek</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Jemima Bleek</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Jemima Bleek notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>Jemima Bleek's 'Hottentot' interviews, 1879</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
