<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>!nanni (XI)</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tamme (XII)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-01</dc:date>
  <dc:description>|xue is afraid of a large bam-bam bird and becomes (or makes) a leopard (!khumm). Woodpigeons, an owl, a korubo and some ||kuorres (small mouse-like animals with cat-like eyes and tail) all laugh at the leopard. The leopard stalks a number of animals and searches for the carcass of a bam-bam bird. At sunset the leopard becomes |xue again and lies down to eat shana. He walks to the water, which is far off. He drinks all the water and shoots a young |ou (a small buck, probably a steenbok), breaking its foreleg. When |xue tries to shoot again his bow breaks. |xue goes to sleep on the bare ground and then makes a new bow from a stick. 1) The latter pages of this story feature pencil translations, presumed to be by D. Bleek; 2) p.9758 opp: (16 December 1880) vocabulary and a description of the |no (a horned wild animal), 3) p.9758v: another name for the lion: 'our country's lion takes offence about his name (if it is mentioned)' - see also The avoidance of the name of the lion (Books V-7 and V-8) for a similar |xam belief; a description of the |hu'nishe, 4) p.9759v: (8 March 1881) a bird which tells the people how to find honey, 5) p.9760v: an interesting note about words for 'being afraid of a woman', 6) p.9763v: the !kun do not strike the lion but shoot it with an arrow, 7) a description of the ||kuo'rre and some of its habits, 8) p.9778v: (21 April 1881) Terms for bravery and timidity; the Makoba put five pieces of feather in their arrows whereas the !kun use three or four pieces, 9) pp.9783v-9785v: see A note on ||kum'm or rain-clouds, 10) p.9786v: 'we are those who refuse to be bound'; a description of evading and throwing others off one's scent, 11) p.9789v: (8 April 1881) see A Bushman drum, 12) p.9792v: (4 April 1881) see Water and wells, 13)  9798v: see Treatment of the old, 14) This story is found in Book XI &amp; XII-10.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/1062</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd !kun notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>|xue and the bam-bam, and as other things</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
