<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>||kabbo (Jantje) (II)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-14</dc:date>
  <dc:description>A girl, when men should not have been looked upon by her for fear of harm to them, saw some people eating together at a rock rabbits house of branches. In consequence of this, they and the house, fixed by her looks, became stars in the sky, and are now to be seen there as the Corona Australis. This myth was told to //kabbos mother by her own mother (L II.-37. 3333-3343). Accounting for the naming of the =nabbe ta !nu (or Corona Australis). The people are sitting around the fire and eating at the Rock Rabbit's (the Dassie's) house. The new maiden looks at them from inside the hut where she is secluded, and they are transfixed (the girl's eye had made the people of the story 'fast') and all become stars. All their things become stars too, including the fire, the house, the Dassie and her children. Therefore the Star-people get the name =nabbe ta !nu or 'house of branches' because they sat at the house's opening in a half-circle when they were transfixed. 1) Note on an insert inside the front cover of Book II-37:  names of places in Bushmanland, '...told to me long ago by Jantje Tooren (or Jantje and Stoffel), and put in here for safety'; also a note on asking ||kabbo about the names of things and the meanings of words, 2) p.3333 opp: this story was told to ||kabbo's mother (!kui-ang) by her mother, 3) p.3334v: a sketch showing the layout of the people, the house, the fire and the food, which would later all become stars and hold these positions in the sky, 4) pp.3335v &amp; 3336v: see A yet unwritten story, about the Rain and one of the First Bushmen girls carried away by a whirlwind and who became a frog, 5) p.3336v: the hare with a red and black tail is also called =nabbe, 6) p.3337v: see ||kabbo's maternal grandmother, who was a !gixa; see also The effect of a new maiden's gaze, 7) p.3339v: the Dassie does not forget the house (in the story) and still makes a house of sticks for its children, 8) This story is found in Book II-37.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/319</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>=nabbe ta !nu (Corona Australis)</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
