<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>|han=kass'o (Klein Jantje) (VIII)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-01</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The !kwai-!kwai, the Mantis, and the Children. The !kwai-!kwai, who was formerly a man, and is now a bird (in appearance somewhat resembling a 'duiker'), comes, during the absence of their parents, to kill the children. They are defended by the Mantis, who causes the death of !kwai-!kwai. By /han#kasso (L VIII.-3. 6304-6322, 4. 6323-6333). A note to the above story was also given by /han#kasso (L VIII.-18. 7596, 7597 and 7595 rev.). The !kwai !kwai bird puts the children into a net, intending to kill them; |kaggen (the Mantis) is at home looking after them. He tells them to sing loudly so that their parents will know something is wrong because they don't normally sing loudly. The parents know something is amiss when they hear their children's voices as well as |kaggen's, and return home. |kaggen has stayed at home with the children because he dreams of the !kwai !kwai's attack on the children and stays at home with them to pull them from the fire the !kwai !kwai tries to roast them in. |kaggen tells the children to burn the !kwai !kwai in the fire, which they do and the |kaggen points out that he is clever even though people are always telling him he is not a 'grown-up person' and always 'gets feathers' and flies away when he sees danger. 1) p.6303v: the !kwai !kwai closely resembles the duiker bird (seen at the Breakwater in Cape Town) and some details about both, 2) p.6310v: on deep and small voices in men, 3) See also A note to the story of the Mantis, the !kwai !kwai and the children, 4) This story is found in Books VIII-3 and VIII-4.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/615</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The !kwai !kwai, the Mantis and the children</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
