<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>Dia!kwain (David Hoesar) (V)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-11</dc:date>
  <dc:description>In former times, when animals were people, the Baboons were jealous of a young Quagga woman, who lived with them, on account of the notice attracted by her great size. For this reason, as well as for her fatness, they killed her, telling the other people that her flesh was that of a young gemsbok. In Katkop dialect, by Dia!kwain, who had it from his father Xaa-ttin (L V.-25. 5993-5997). The Punishment of the Baboon, which appears to be a continuation of the above fable, was narrated to Dia!kwain by an older female relation named Ttuobboken !kaugn (L V.-24. 5974-5991). An explanatory note to the story of the Punishment of the Baboon was also given by Dia!kwain from information received from his mother, =kamme-an (L V.-24. 5992). When the Quagga was a person she resembled a boulder and the Baboons feared her size and killed her. 1) p.5993 opp: Dia!kwain heard this story from his father (Xaa-ttin); sieves made from matting (used by 'real Bushmen') and skins, used by Koranna and 'Grass Bushmen', 2) pp.5994v-5995v: see Quagga makes flour, 3) p.5996v: |xam names for the 'real' quagga and the 'striped' quagga, 4) See also The woman eaten by baboons: a fragment of the account and Baboons who ate human beings, 5) This story is found in Book V-25.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/558</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The woman who was killed by the Baboons</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
