<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>||axas or ||axa (V)</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dabi</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Martha</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-02</dc:date>
  <dc:description>Reporters' Note Book. Naron language notebook. Short narratives concerning daily life and rituals - especially menstruation, marriage, birth, healing, rain, treatment of bones and hunting; some words and sentences. Photographs mentioned. 1) p.001-008:  A list of 21 Bushman names [appears to be referring to a photographic plate in a book, see p.004]  numbered with some details of personal history and names of relations, eg. =axas ti =nusha (1), Namma |kai (2), Ho |kai and Gei |kup (3) etc.; 2) p.009 and 010: names and personal history as well as descriptions of artefacts and customs eg. ornaments worn by women; 3) p.011-016: Naron words and sentences with odd bits of personal history; 4) p.016: Films (photographs) numbered 1-6 with brief descriptions; 5) p.018-023: 21.1.21. ||axas [?]; 6) p.0024: ||axa (V) on marriage customs and presents exchanged; 7) p.027-30: continued from 317, ||axas on 4.3.22 - what the old people, the old men did, and knew, how they worked rain, 'they did not teach the younger generation about the rain', healing and about 'Kaffirs' (doctors) and where the dead go (those who die quickly and slowly), about magic, illness;  8) p. 032-33: words and sentences, customs concerning love, marriage and fighting (in relation to latter), 9) p.034: 5th March; 10) p.037-042: 5.3.21. ||axas and Martha describe menstruation and birth customs, description of menstruation ritual, 'Bushmen girls are big when it comes - about 15...', 'girls are often married before the first menses', sex before marriage, remarrying and burying children, birth and cutting the cord ritual, weaning; 11) p.043-047: Dabi. Hunting and cooking porcupine, treatment of bones and entrails, food sharing, wounding and protection of shooting fingers, snare, presentiments, eating jackals' hearts..</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/2035</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Dorothea Bleek notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>Dorothea Bleek - Book BC151_A3_011</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
