<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:date>2020-08-29</dc:date>
  <dc:description>||khwai-hemm tells this story of his fight with |kaggen (the Mantis) on the hunting-ground. |kaggen is peacefully hunting when he mistakenly crosses the spoor of !goe !kweitentu. !goe !kweitentu and |kaggen fight. |kaggen then visits the Ticks but they fall upon him and beat him in anger (because they are 'black'). |kaggen flies away into the water telling his things to follow him and then takes away the Ticks' things while they are sleeping so that they might feel hunger and cold. He comes home to his wife and Ichneumon laughs at him because he has been beaten, thinking he is the one who started the fighting. The visit of the Mantis to the houses of the Ticks, - who, excepting one boy, have hidden themselves away in the fleeces of their sheet, -evil thoughts of the Mantis with regard to this boy, who is left in charge of the pots of food which are upon the fire, -return of the Ticks, -their attack upon the Mantis, -his flight home, -his revenge upon the Ticks for their inhospitality and ill-treatment of him, -the consequent destitution of the Ticks, which is lamented by the relatives of the Mantis, -the monster //khwai-hemm is now, by the wish of the Mantis, unwillingly summoned by his daughter, the Porcupine, to swallow for them a portion of the Ticks flock of sheep,- his fearful appearance and unlimited voracity, -he swallows the Mantis, and the brave /kwammana as well, -fiery trial of the young sons of the Mantis and /kwammana by the Porcupine, -the monster //khwai-hemm slain, -re-appearance of all the animals and things which had just been swallowed by him, -removal of the survivors from the place where he lay dead. (L II. - 32. 2916-2965, 33. 2966-3057, 34. 3058-3149, translated). The monster //khwai-hemms speech to the Mantis and the reply of the latter are given separately. (B XXIII. 2161-2210, 2234-2247).</dc:description>
  <dc:identifier>stories/88</dc:identifier>
  <dc:title>The monster ||khwai-hemm's speech</dc:title>
</oai_dc:dc>
