<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:contributor>The New Digital Bleek and Lloyd</dc:contributor>
  <dc:creator>||kabbo (Jantje) (II)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-15</dc:date>
  <dc:description>An ignorant man having gone to dig up Sho-!oa, is discovered speechless and motionless, sitting among serpents, by the hole where he had been digging. By a skilful application of Sho-!oa, the snakes are driven away, taking with them the scent which had injured the man, but leaving the other scent with the plant in the hole. The man is (also by Sho-|oa) restored to speech and motion (L. II.-36. 3287-3332). The scent of the Ssho |oa plant is then taken away by snakes (which go into the hole that the Ssho |oa was dug out of). The notes accompanying this story describe other things relating to Ssho |oa, such as the Ssho |oa snake. The people never kill Ssho |oa snakes. ||kabbo was told not to dig for Ssho |oa because he didn't have the neccessary marks. 1) Note on the inside of the cover of Book II-36: pp.3242-3332 were translated in September 1873, but Lloyd 'Began to enter from p.3261 Aug. 1st 1911.', 2) p.3290v: ||kabbo uses the term 'nephew' in the story, but he means friend, 3) pp.3296v &amp; 3297v: see On women's hunting or '|kua', 4) pp.3309v &amp; 3310v: the |ki ||en live on the colonial side of the Orange River (who speak |xam and Koranna) and have the marks of a 'ssho |o a's man', (called |nu ka |a |a), 5) See also About Ssho |oa: where to be found and How women fear the new Ssho |oa which has just been brought home and The consequences of a woman's smelling fresh Ssho |oa scent and Ssho |oa and What the man does and says to the new Ssho |oa so that it may know him, 6) This story is found in Book II-36.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/316</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>An ignorant man digs up Ssho |oa and the consequences of his actions</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
