<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:contributor>The New Digital Bleek and Lloyd Archive</dc:contributor>
  <dc:creator>||kabbo (Jantje) (II)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-20</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The Day's Heart star buries his child alive and goes away. Other creatures come by including the child's mother. The father gives the daughter directions in a speech in which he tells her her name and the doings of various animals and stars, such as ||ko hai. He also tells her about the behaviour of people and what they must do in their daily lives with food and so on, and about the heavens and their creation. The Stars are divided into night stars and dawn stars ... The 'Dawns Heart' (the star Jupiter) has a daughter, who is identified with some neighbouring star preceding Jupiter (at the time when we asked, it was Regulus or Alpha Leonis). Her name is the 'Dawns-Heart-child', and her relation to her father is somewhat mysterious. Besides a short statement of the nature of the Dawns-Heart, and of his child (L II.-2. 292 and 293), we have two long pieces. The first of these begins with a short narrative of only eleven columns, and then gives a very long discourse from the Dawns-Heart to his daughter, which treats not only of their own history and that of the lynx-mother, but also of the Sun, Moon, and Stars, and of the habits of different animals. 1) The Day's Heart star is also known as the Dawn's-Heart star (in Specimens of Bushman Folklore), 2) p.1444v: a note on the kaross, which has arms with which to fasten it in front, 3) pp.1439v-1440v and p.1445v: see Jewellery and ornaments worn by women, 4) p.1502v: the term 'great' means that the Day's Heart star is grown-up, 5) p.1505v: the place where day breaks, 6) p.1523v: the people cut the game into flaps of flesh, 7) p.1524v: the flesh is beaten and softened after it has dried in the sun, 8) p.1527v: ||kabbo says that wet flesh and dry rice are mixed by pounding them together; people thirst after eating dry rice, 9) p.1528v: houses are made of trees and bushes, 10) p.1529v: Brinkkop, 11) p.1530v: the screen of bushes in which men lie and wait for ostriches and other animals, 12) p.1542v: Kleine Har River, 13) p.1547v: the Groote Hart River and Groote Doorn Boom as well as the names of things in the story, 14) See also More about the Day's Heart star: what he says to his daughter and The story of !ko'-g !nuin-tara or !ko'-g !nuin-tara and the Day's Heart star and Day's Heart and The Day-Heart star child, 15) This story is found in Books II-15 and II-16.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/256</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The Day's Heart star</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
