<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>Dia!kwain (David Hoesar) (V)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-12</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The young man of the ancient race, who was carried off by a Lion, when asleep in the field. A very affecting legend, in the Katkop dialect, related to Dia!kwain by his mother =kamme-an (L V.-7. 4457-4525). The Lion places the young man in a tree and goes off to get water to drink. The Lion spies on the man and sees him move and decides to drink quickly and run back to eat him. The man springs from the tree and runs home where the people wrap him in hartebeest skins and mats and hide him in the house's 'bush-screen'. The Lion comes and the people shoot at it, but it is not harmed. Eventually the people tire of trying to kill the Lion and ask the man's mother to give her son to the Lion. As the Lion kills the man the people shoot and stab it and it dies. 1) Dia!kwain heard this story from his mother (=kamme-an), 2) Date on p.4457: 29 March; p.4503: 4 April, 3) p.4461v: about the Swart-Storm tree (in Dutch) (the tree the man was placed in by the Lion), 4)  p.4498v: the baking of !kui-sse roots in a heated and covered hole in the ground, 5) p.4499v: the old woman's fire will be on top of the hole that contains the baking !kui-sse, 6) See also The man who went to sleep when out hunting alone, 7) This story is found in Book V-7.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/420</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The Lion and the man's story; what the Lion formerly did to the man or The young man of the Ancient Race, who was carried off by a Lion, when asleep in the field</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
