<item type="story"><id>932</id>
<collection>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</collection>
<title>The song of the young woman, as she returned home</title>
<summary><i>The Young Woman of the early race whose breast was caught in a cleft of the rock. Her escape from the Two Lions. By /han≠kass’o (L VIII.-32. 8821-8842).</i> She sings &apos;My nipple shall grow into shape again&apos; so that her breast will return to the way it had been (before it got caught in the rock). </summary><comments>1) See also <i>The young woman who disobeyed her mother, and fell in with the two Lions (!haue ta ≠hou and !gu) </i>and also p.8822v, 2) This story is found in Book VIII-32</comments><date>26 November 1879</date><storypages>8841-8842</storypages><category>History (Early Race)</category><category>Poetry</category><author>|han≠kass'o (Klein Jantje) (VIII)</author><keyword><kw>young woman</kw><subkw>who disobeyed her mother and fell in with the two Lions</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>young woman</kw><subkw>the song she sings as she returns home</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>young woman</kw><subkw>sings for her nipple to grow back and for her breast to return to the way it was</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>song</kw><subkw>sung by the young woman as she returns home to her breast</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>song</kw><subkw>of the young woman who disobeyed her mother and fell in with the two Lions</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>breast</kw><subkw>the young woman sings for hers to return to the way it was</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>breast</kw><subkw>the young woman sings for her nipple to grow back</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>breast</kw><subkw>in the song of the young woman as she returned home</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>Early Race</kw><subkw>or First Bushmen</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>Early Race</kw><subkw>and the song of the young woman of, as she returned home</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>woman</kw><subkw>the song of the young woman, as she returned home</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>woman</kw><subkw>the young woman of the Early Race who disobeyed her mother and fell in with the two Lions</subkw></keyword>

<page><file>A2_1_107_08841.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_107</book></page>
<page><file>A2_1_107_08842.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_107</book></page>
</item>
