<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>!nanni (XI)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-12</dc:date>
  <dc:description>|xue is water, a lizard, grass, a |nu-erre bird, a dead elephant, a buffalo, a tsan, an Omuherero and a snake (a ||ge). |xue makes reeds at the water and grabs one of the woodpigeons. |xue becomes |xue and rises up and grabs the bitten woodpigeon and plucks out its feathers, putting them on his head. |xue puts the woodpigeon's body on hot embers and eats it. He hears an Ovaherero and hides. |xue flies away to his mother's country where he sees his father. |xue's mother and father become afraid of him and run away. |xue chases his father, all the while loudly speaking the Berg Damara language. |xue fears the large black reeds where his father hides. |xue sits and drinks water from a little hole and cries for his father. His father sees him, but leaves because |xue is an Omuherero. |xue searches for his father and cries when he does not find him. 1) p.9403v: !nanni heard this story from his paternal grandfather (Karu); for an illustration of this story see !nanni's picture of 10 April 1880 picturing a smoking |xue and some =ne=nebbi or woodpigeons (NLLB_D_!n024), 2) p.9404v: (16 June 1880) !nanni describes an errand he ran on the previous day to Dr. Stewart, 3) p.9410v: (!nanni) 'When the rain comes, the wind is great, and when the rain goes away, the wind is small'; 'It is not the earth's water, but is the sky's water', 4) p.9416v: see |uma and Da: the names of their parents, 5) p.9428v: Tamme thinks |uma is the 'child of |xue'; a certain fungus (gabaka) which women eat and men fear, 6) This story is found in Book XI &amp; XII-6.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/1036</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd !kun notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>|xue, his father and changes</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
