<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>||kabbo (Jantje) (II)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-01</dc:date>
  <dc:description>Shó-|õä, a Bushman vegetable medicine, used also as a charm (L II.-36. 3242-3261). How one man fights with another, having previously rubbed his own hands with Shó-|õä; and how he afterwards restores the man with whom he fought, by means of a fresh application of Shó-|õä (L II.-36. 3262-3268). A detailed description of the properties and applications of Ssho |oa, including its medicinal uses, its use as a preparation for hunting and as a charm for hunting springbok. 1) Inserts on the inside of the front cover of Book II-36: notes concerning animals and the making of bowstrings from the sinews of buck; a note on the heart falling down when a man is ill or when he is startled awake from sleep; what |kaggen does when an eland has been shot; see What |kaggen does when an eland has been shot, 2) Note on the inside of the cover of Book II-36: pp.3242-3332 were translated in September 1873, but Lloyd 'Began to enter from p.3261 Aug. 1st 1911.', 3) Date on p.3262: 20 September, 4) pp.3244v &amp; 3245v: see How Korannas and the |xam cut themselves in order to shoot well, 5) p.3246v: although the story refers to coal being rubbed into cuts, it is actually burnt wood in powdered form, 6) p.3250v: a man aimed at and missed a springbok because he left his band at the house: he has to cut his arm so that the arrow will fly well and make the right (tearing) noise, 7) p.3251v: if the arrow flies badly it makes a whistling and hissing noise; the hunter draws the Ssho |oa in a line down the centre of his forehead, down his nose and across the right nostril to the middle of his right cheek, 8) p.3255v: the 'dust's fear': what the springbok feel when running closely together in the dust, 9) p.3258v: hunters head off the springbok, 10) p.3261v: a word for help and what ||kabbo calls 'white man's talk' for the same thing, 11) p.3263v: the overcome man's eyes have rolled back in his head (go behind themselves); the fighter has rubbed his underarms with Ssho |oa before fighting and then rubbed the other's face; 12) p.3264v: the perspiration and the Ssho |oa mix under his arms and smell together; the fighter revives his afflicted opponent and gives the man the piece of Ssho |oa he has doctored him with, 13) See also About Ssho |oa: where to be found and An ignorant man digs up Ssho |oa and the consequences of his actions and How women fear the new Ssho |oa which has just been brought home and The consequences of a woman's smelling fresh Ssho |oa scent and What the man does and says to the new Ssho |oa so that it may know him, 14) This story is found in Book II-36.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/309</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>Ssho |oa or ||karruken-||karruken or |u ssho a</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
