<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>Dia!kwain (David Hoesar) (V)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-12</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The Maiden who would not listen to her parents, and was punished, together with those around her, by the angry Rain. In the Katkop dialect, by Dia!kwain (L V.-13. 4981-5022). A story about the Early Race (the !khwe ||na ss'e !k'e) and the Rain, when the Porcupine was a man and how it came by the quills on its back and neck. The Porcupine's sister is a new maiden and behaves disobediently, and the Rain becomes angry and kills with lightning because it feels the girl does not protect the people. The brother must address the angry Rain in an effort to direct it to a different place. The new maiden is caught in a storm, even though she had been told not to go out. She is taken up by a whirlwind and becomes a snake. 1) p.4981 opp: this story was told to Dia!kwain by his mother (=kamme-an), 2) p.5006v: a lengthy note on the edible (but bitter and hairy) !koa root; it is dug out of clay and then prepared for eating, 3) p.5018v: the new maiden in the story was transformed by the Rain into a kind of large snake (||kheten) whose name is feared, 4) p.5020v: another name (!nuin) by which people refer to the feared snake, 5) See also How the brother of the maiden taken up in a whirlwind became the Porcupine; followed by various remarks about porcupines and Rain changes people into frogs, 6) This story is found in Book V-13.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/452</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publishers>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publishers>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The maiden who was taken up in a whirlwind by the agency of the angry Rain and became a great snake</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
