<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>Anni u</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>|ki ke</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>|kaiku</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>≠nabbe ta mas (Lena)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-01</dc:date>
  <dc:description>Reporters' Note Book. Naron language notebook. Words and sentences, some personal history. Reference made to recordings made by DB. Some information regarding customs and daily life. 1) p.01-05: Tsaxas, words and sentences including different peoples in the area and their languages; 2) p.05: 'Bushmen pushed more into the desert by the Hottentots further into the desert'; 3) p.07: reference to Stow pictures; 4) p.08: Bushmen who were servants of the Masarwa; 5) p.09-011: Names and personal history of ≠nabbe ta mas or Lena, men's and women's dances, different groups of Bushmen and their languages, customs, poisons and artefacts used by her people; 6) p.012: 'Dance to melody of Elandbull dance', roles played by men and women and dress, tattooing description; 7) p.013: reference to numbered records (recordings); 8) p.015: 28.3.1920. Vichanas [?]. Names and descriptions of people, some of them Naron-speakers; 9) p.018: names and personal history of various people; 10) p.019: Some history of the region, and some of the people who live there (Vichanas[?]), |kaiku a Naron-speaker who grew up there and some of his personal history; 11) p0.22: Vichenas[?] 29.3.21; 12) p.033: said on Record IX: 'the man who wanted to marry her first had a big swelling on the jaw[?] so she would not marry him', 'I had two kinders but they both died.', 'he had killed a jackal in the veld and eaten it up...'; 13) p.036: 16.11.21. Sandfontein. Words including plants and flowers; 14) p.040: Anni u [?] 18.11.21; 15) p.044-057: Anni u 19.11.21.  Mostly names of and uses for plants eg. buchu; 16) p.058: 22.11.21. Anni u gives an account of a man travelling by wagon and donkey, words; 17) p.062-064: 'The question has often been put to me: what use can be made of the Bushmen?' [looks to be an article or a report by DB in very rough form]; 18) p.065: continued from 22[?], !nau - about catching food with a trap; 19) p.066: 23.11.21. |ki ke. Featuring some details of personal history; 20) p.071: 24.11.21. |kwi kui;  21) p.076: Anni u. 24.11.21; 22) p.080-081: 25.11.21.  About the rain: 'rain falls much rain a deal of rain the rain speaks, the rain cries out thunder, in the sky the sky's water comes down water will lie in the pan'; 23) p.083-084: 'the little bird becomes a wizard', about birds, jackals and other things eaten, digging a well, ants, snails etc;  24) p.088: 28.11.21. Anni u.  Words including smoking, wearing karosses; 25) p.090: 29.11.21. Doebo [?] includes some personal history, his travels; 26) p. 091: Anni u. 30.11.21.  About Babi xaa, a Naron-speaker who also speaks the White man's language..</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/2034</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Dorothea Bleek notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>Dorothea Bleek - Book BC151_A3_010</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
