<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>||kabbo (Jantje) (II)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-11</dc:date>
  <dc:description>|kaggen (the Mantis) deceives the young girl-children by becoming a hartebeest and feigning death. The children are delighted to find meat and make knives to cut it up. Then they skin and cut up |kaggen's flesh, which moves around. They place it on a bush then bundle up the flesh and carry it off home. As they go along the hartebeest winks and its head talks to the girl who carries it, asking her to remove the thong in its eye. The children get a fright and drop the bundles of flesh. |kaggen starts reattaching all the dismembered parts of his body. He becomes a man and chases the children. The children run home and tell their father what happened to the dead hartebeest. |kaggen leaves them and goes into the river bed to return to his own house. The father asks if they had cut up |kaggen who pretended to be the dead hartebeest. The children are tired from running away from |kaggen and do not hunt for food but stay at home. 1) pp.2287v-2289v: a note about extracting poison from a wounded man's flesh which also 'quivers' or moves (see When a man's flesh moves), 2) p.2292v: a note mentioning |kaggen's 'special speech',  3) p.2293v: a note on |kaggen's way of talking, 4) p.2299: curses used by the Flat Bushmen, 5) p.2331v: a note on |xam names of gambro and 'Bushman rice' (which are 'hunted' by women), 6) See also The hartebeest resembles the Mantis and The hartebeest and the eland belong to the Mantis (in Lloyd's notebooks), 7) This story is found in Book XXIV.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/101</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Wilhelm Bleek</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Wilhelm Bleek</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Wilhelm Bleek notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The Mantis turned into a hartebeest</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
