<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>||kabbo (Jantje) (II)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-12</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The Ichneumon, |kaggen (the Mantis) and |kwammana go to the Lion's house. |kaggen is afraid and hides in a bag. He frightens a little Lion who looks into the bag and the mother Lion grows angry with |kaggen. The Ichneumon throws |kaggen into the sky and he flies away calling for the Hartebeest children to follow him. He tells his wife and the Porcupine that the Lion has killed |kwammana and the Ichneumon, but the Ichneumon and |kwammana come home carrying meat. Another myth, running out of one of the versions of the myth of the Eland, is the account of a visit which !kwammana and the Ichneumon pay to the Lions house, and on which the Mantis accompanies them, but behaves, of course, in a mode appropriate to his mythological character, whereby he incurs the wrath of the mother-lioness, and has to take flight. On his return home, he alarms his wife and adopted daughter by false reports of the death of his two companions, who, however, soon appear upon the scene, alive and hearty, laden with presents of quaggas flesh (L II.-4. 519-529, II.-5. 530-546). 1) Date on p.528: 28 September; p.536: 28 September; p.541: 29 September, 2) |kwammana is spelt in various ways, such as '|kwamman-a' and '|kammanga', 3) This story is found in Books II-4 and II-5.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/210</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The Mantis, the Ichneumon and |kammanga go to Lion's house</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
