<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:contributor>The New Digital Bleek and Lloyd Archive</dc:contributor>
  <dc:creator>Dia!kwain (David Hoesar) (V)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-20</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The Bushman Doctor or Sorcerer (L II.-1. 273-275).  An account of these people was also given in the Katkop dialect by Dia!kwain (L V.-3. 4122-4131), from whom we besides have two reports of cures performed upon himself. The first of these (L V.-3. 4132-4161, 4. 4162-4199) includes a speech made by the sorceress; the second relates how she cured him when injured by a Kafir (L V.-4. 4200-4230). The healer (or !gixa) !kwarra-an heals ('snores') Dia!kwain. Afterwards she tells his mother all about her work and complains about her treatment by the people. The healer does not wish to do good work because she is angry that the people do not pay her. There are additional notes about 'sneezing' (|kamma) and what comes out afterwards. 1) p.4131v: this happened to Dia !kwain when he was about eleven years old; the sorceress told this to his mother at the time when she cured him, 2) p.4135v: other sorcerers can take one 'quite' away, or kill a person, 3) p.4138v: a note in Dutch on Tornan Manier, or 'sorcerer's craft', 4) p.4155v: the name of a red stone (told to Dia!kwain by his mother), 5) p.4168v: the |xam name of a certain cricket, 6) p.4188v: about 'sneezing' (|kamma), 7) p.4190v: directing the contents of the sneeze, or sneezing 'rightly', 8) See also About the sorceress !kwarra-an and The story of a sorceress: that which she did when the Kafir had hurt my throat, she 'snored' me, when my throat was swollen and About sorcerers: when the sorcerer returns home after his work is done, 9) This story is found in Books V-3 and V-4.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/397</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The tale of a wise person or sorceress, what she said, when she talked with us</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
