<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:contributor>The New Digital Bleek and Lloyd Archive</dc:contributor>
  <dc:creator>||kabbo (Jantje) (II)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-20</dc:date>
  <dc:description>A girl of the ancient race (preceding the Bushmen) wished for a little light, so that the people might see to return home by night.  She, therefore, threw wood-ashes into the sky, which became the Milky Way. This myth, which //kabbo heard from his mother !kwi-an (L II.-28. 2505-2516), is followed by an account of the same girl, who, being vexed with her mother for giving her too little of a certain red edible root, threw up portions of it into the sky, where they became stars (L II.-28.  2516-2520). A verso note on p.2516v describes how this girl (the new maiden) made locusts by throwing the peel of the !kui ssi that she was eating into the sky. Another note describes how she threw up the !huin roots to make stars. The red (or old) !huin made red stars and the white or young !huin made white stars. 1) Note on the inside of the cover of Book II-28: pp.2505-2596. From 17 January 1873. pp.2509-2565 translated in 1914; 'To get the story of some of the first Bushmen who persuaded a young relation to enter the skin of a little animal somewhat like a mouse; they fitted on the skin carefully and finished it off; soon it became a lion, and ate one of the first Bushmen women; and then, I think, later, became one of the Lion Stars in heaven.', 2) This story was told to ||kabbo by his mother (!kui ang), 3) Reverse of frontispiece (Book II-28): 'This girl is said to be one of the !khwe-|na-ssho-!k'e, and the 'first' girl; and to have acted ill; she was finally shot by her husband. These !khwe-|na-ssho-!k'e are said to have been stupid, and not to have understood things well', 4) The !huin root is eaten by baboons and porcupines, 5) pp.2520v &amp; 2521v: see The treatment of the 'growing' girl, 7) See also The new maiden who threw !huin into the sky; which became stars, and the wood ashes which were upon it, the Milky Way, 8) This story is found in Book II-28.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/285</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The girl who made the Milky Way, by throwing ashes into the sky</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
