<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:descriptions>One of the ancient people preceding the Bushmen brought home a lion’s cub, telling his wife that it was a dog which his younger brother had given him, and that it was the whelp of a dog which killed gemsbok. She, however, knew that it was the son of a lioness, whose voice was known to her of old, and who was now heard roaring for her lost cub. The man called it by the name of !kuisse !khwí /kü.  Although, in hunting gemsbok, the man was well</dc:descriptions>
  <dc:descriptions>frightened by his pretended dog, and had even to get his wife to throw fire at it on his return home, he still maintained to her that it was a dog. The wife prudently sent their little son with his father, when he went out early the next morning to hunt. After this, they went hunting gemsbok many times, the boy in fear and trembling, and his father in continual danger; until one day the boy saw his father killed by !kuisse !khwí |kü, who had now grown into a large young lion. He himself, after having seen the lion carry off his father’s body, and lay it under a thorn–tree, with that of a gemsbok which it had also killed, makes his escape home. Upon her son’s report of the death of her husband, and his warning to herself that the Lion will soon be upon them, the widow goes away with her children to the house of her husband’s father. On the following morning, the boy goes with his uncles to see what has been done to the deserted homestead. They sleep that night on a mountain above the old home, and the next morning, not seeing any lions, they visit the hut, the sticks of which are a good deal disturbed. They discover the spoor of seven lions (viz, !kuisse !khwí /kü, his parents, his two brothers, and two sisters). After a visit to the scene of the calamity, they stealthily retrace their steps home, and remove to a different place. This legend is told with great epic breadth, in a very vivid manner, giving an excellent picture of Bushman life; and it is seasoned with many dialogues, in which the wife is a particularly characteristic speaker (L II.</dc:descriptions>
  <dc:descriptions>26. 2320</dc:descriptions>
  <dc:descriptions>2412, 27. 2413</dc:descriptions>
  <dc:descriptions>2504, 29. 2597</dc:descriptions>
  <dc:descriptions>2687, 30. 2688</dc:descriptions>
  <dc:descriptions>2779, 31. 2780</dc:descriptions>
  <dc:descriptions>2873 1/2).</dc:descriptions>
  <dc:identifiers>283</dc:identifiers>
  <dc:title>The story of !khwe</dc:title>
  <dc:title>|na ssho</dc:title>
  <dc:title>!kui: the man who took a young Lion, and made use of it as a dog ( a story of the First Bushman)</dc:title>
</oai_dc:dc>
