<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:description>The Mantis and |kw mmana go out visiting together.  The Mantis involves himself in a quarrel with a young  Dasse  (Hyrax), and stones fall upon him and |kw mmana.  The latter, upon whom they lie loosely, is first rescued; while the Mantis owes his rescue to the entreaties of his wife, who prevails upon the people to take him out. His teasing and troublesome ways are much blamed. (L VIII. 2. 6165 6193, and 6195.)  Another version of the story of the Crow Messengers appears, here, in connexion with the adventure related above;  |kw mmana and his companion being, in this instance, those who were found by the successful bird (Corvus scapulatus). (L VIII. 2.  6147 6157) By the same narrator was also given the Rescue of |kw mmana  and the Mantis, and their return home.  The Blue Crane, who is the elder sister of |kaggen, pities his sad condition. Specimens of the peculiar manner in which the Bushman language is spoken by the wife of |kaggen, and by the Ichneumon, respectively, are here given.  (L VIII. 2. 6196 6231, 3. 6232 6236.) A note regarding the  kam !kw , a member of the party which went to the rescue of /kw mmana and his companion (L VII.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>2. 6195 rev. and 6196 rev.). |kwammana and |kaggen (the Mantis) both drink from ostrich egg</dc:description>
  <dc:description>shells offered to them, |kwammana by the young bee and |kaggen by the Dassie who passes water into his shell. |kaggen curses the Dassie when he tastes its urine and the mother Dassie makes rocks roll on |kaggen and |kwammana. The people take |kaggen out from under the rocks only because his wife has asked them to.</dc:description>
  <dc:identifier>610</dc:identifier>
  <dc:title>The Mantis and |kwammana visit the Dassie's house</dc:title>
</oai_dc:dc>
