<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>Tamme (XII)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-11</dc:date>
  <dc:description>Tamme contributes words and sentences relating to everyday life in his country. The list includes !kun terms for weapons (especially arrows and arrow-making), parts of the body, plants and animals, cooking utensils, colours, numbers, weather, relations and words gained from contact with Europeans (such as tinderboxes and whipping). The names of !nanni's four brothers and sisters are noted and there are other references to the boys' personal experiences, including a fragment of a song !nanni sings when weeding, an occasional mention of the boys' parents, how |han=kass'o 'takes' Tamme to 'sleep', how Tamme's father is dead and so on. |han=kass'o has provided |xam equivalents for some of the !kun vocabulary and some of the notes on the verso pages are made by !nanni. 1) Loose inserts on the insideof the front cover of Book XI &amp; XII-2 include: a note about a man who says that !nanni's parents are living whereas Tamme's were killed by the Ovambo, and that Erickson at Ohlssons Wiederberg brought 'them' out; another note features their names, 2) Date on p.9051: 2 September, 3) p.9137v: see The Moon, the Sun and the stars, 4) This story is found in Book XI &amp; XII-2.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/959</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd !kun notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>Words and sentences: given by Tamme</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
