<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>||kabbo (Jantje) (II)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-02 17:22:23.150900</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The Anteater inquires from a flock of springbok ewes, one after another, whether her child is a female. Each mother answers that hers is a male, until, at last, a foolish Springbok confesses that her child is a daughter. The Anteater offers to hold the child, so that the Springbok should eat some of the Anteater's food. The latter then springs into a hole with the kid, and tells the mother, who is crying for her child, to go. The male Springbok scolds his wife for having lost their child. The Anteater then lays down the law with regard to the proper food for different animals, and that their marriages should be suitable. They all listen to the Anteater, and also to the Lynx, who repeats to them the Anteaters words. In the discourse there is imbedded a fable about the knorhaan, relating to how its head was burnt in the fire; but this requires further explanation. (L II.-3. 406-416.) On account of her husbands anger, the Springbok mother sends the Lynx to recover her child for her. The Lynx slips into the Anteaters hole underneath the young Springbok, and, pushing her out, runs off with her. The Anteater, trying to follow, is caught in the bowstring of the Lynx, as in a sling.  Disengaging herself, she again proceeds to deliver to the Lynx her important messages concerning the nature and habits of the different animals. 1) pp. 406-415: 'translated (with the help of David Hoesar) March 4th 1875', 2) see also The Anteater, Springbok and Lynx (||kabbo's version 1) and The Anteater's story or The Anteater, Springbok, Lynx and Partridge and The Anteater's laws (||kabbo's version 2) and The Korhaan marries his elder sister (the Anteater's laws) (||kabbo's version 2), 3) This story is found in Book II-3.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/197</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The Anteater, Springbok and Lynx (||kabbo's version 2)</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
