<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>|han=kass'o (Klein Jantje) (VIII)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-11</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The Young Woman of the early race whose breast was caught in a cleft of the rock. Her escape from the Two Lions. By /han=kasso (L VIII.-32. 8821-8842). A tale of the Early Race in which a lazy young woman's breast gets stuck in the cleft of a rock. The two Lions (!haue ta =hou and !gu) approach her (intending to kill her), but she convinces them to go and drink water before eating her. She commands the water to 'Go away yonder!' and the Lions follow it in vain. She cuts off her nipple, releasing her breast from the rock, and pounds it together with !kai from the Lions' bag to make two balls which she leaves at the rock. When the Lions return they wonder where the girl has gone. Her nipple ball answers 'I am her!'. The two Lions spend the night trying to catch the girl and hurting their teeth biting at the rocks. 1) p.8820v: |han=kass'o heard this from his mother (|xabbi-an), 2) p.8821v: see Note on lizards; what people call a little stick, 3) p.8822v: (24 November 1879) the song of the young woman who was cursed by her mother, 4) p.8825v: crows and death; see Birds await the death of a thing, 5) p.8826v: (23 November 1879) spoiling water; the names of two stars; parts of the human ear, 6) p.8827v: the Lions formerly used stone knives, 7) p.8828v: |han=kass'o speculates about !kai; how people make 'meal' of meat when springbok are numerous, 8) p.8837v: !gu is the Lion who understood, 9) See also Note on the two Lions and The song of the young woman, as she returned home, 10) This story is found in Book VIII-32.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/929</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The young woman who disobeyed her mother, and fell in with the two Lions (!haue ta =hou and !gu)</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
