<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>|a!kunta (Stoffel) (I)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-01</dc:date>
  <dc:description>A man kills an Ostrich and takes the body home to his wife, who removes its feathers. A gust of wind carries a feather up into the sky after which it falls into the water and gets wet. Here it becomes an Ostrich again which then leaves the water. On land it grows and strengthens and calls loudly for wives. It marries the wives who then lay eggs. One wife lies on her egg while the male Ostrich guards the house from the Jackal and the Hyena who want to steal the eggs. The male Ostrich goes away and the Hyena frightens away the Ostrich wives, takes the eggs and puts them in the bushes. The Jackal fears the male Ostrich who kicks at her with his feet and runs away into the bushes. The Hyena thinks she has frightened away the Ostrich and may return to hunt for eggs, as she is hungry. The angry Ostrich confronts the Hyena, who runs away. The Hyena returns to the Ostrich's house to seek food. 1) p.1182v: the names of the Bastards who took ||kabbo's place (or home), 2) p.1239v: a note added on 17 November 1872, 3) p.1244v: |xam names and a description of Venus and Jupiter, 4) p.1261v: the |xam name of Sirius; 'honey's songs' as well as songs to the stars; 'That is Bushman's work to talk to the stars', 5) p.1262v: |xam names of Sirius, Canopus and Pleiades and the name of the stone that the digging stick is fitted into, 6) p.1282v: note added on 24 November 1872, 7) p.1300v: greetings in |xam, 8) p.1329v: some information about =kasin (Klaas Katkop) who was the son of ||xarra-|hun and yoa =ko, 9) This story is found in Book XII, Book XIII and Book XIV.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/60</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Wilhelm Bleek notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>Resurrection of the He-Ostrich</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
