<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>=kasin (Klaas Katkop) (IV)</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>||kabbo (Jantje) (II)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-01</dc:date>
  <dc:description>Different Bushman Medicines; where found; and their uses. Only the names of these medicines are given in Bushman, and the remarks respecting them in English, after =kasin (L IV.-1. 3425-3440). These specimens were found in the hut of a Bushman sorcerer, and were kindly furnished for identification by Mr. J Gibb. //kabbos names for the same specimens, with his remarks (in English only), are in a separate paper of 7 folio pages, to which =kasins notes have been also briefly added, in red ink. A series of numbered entries describing the making of preparations from, as well as the use and collection of, various plants and insects for the treatment of a variety of ailments by the |xam. 1) Insert pasted inside the front cover of Book IV-1: a note to ask the informants whether 'Hottentots' (from =kasin) do agricultural work and use a digging stick or whether (from ||kabbo) the |xam may hunt on each other's land; also an insert dictated by ||kabbo on the collecting of a grub by 'Grass Bushmen', which is then made into something called |kai ka !gaoken, probably a poison or medicine to be used with caution, 2) See also the insert pasted inside the back cover of Book IV concerning various medicinal plants - their names, their uses and where they are found, 3) Date on p.3439: 4 November, 4) p.3437v: possibly the name of a river or stream near =kasin's place (!kuirri) where a certain plant grows, 5) This story is found in Book IV-1.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/331</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>Medicines taken by the ill</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
