<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:contributor>The New Digital Bleek and Lloyd Archive</dc:contributor>
  <dc:creator>Hokan (Janike)</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Klaas (Guiman)</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>=nanni (Anna)</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>!karre an (Katren)</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>!kommanan !a (Klaas)</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>|xaken-an (Mikki Streep)</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kaiki</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Katrina</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Rachel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jan</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bet</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>|numni (Trinki)</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kyky (Willem)</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>!kwe |kake (Doorki)</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>!kun !we (Sabina)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-20</dc:date>
  <dc:description>Notebook. Includes some words and sentences. Mostly personal history (genealogies, and places of of contributors and their relations). Customs, especially burial practises. A segment of a diary of DB. Contributions taken from conversations with people at Stuurman's pits, Eyerdoppan etc. 1) p. 164 &amp; 165: 28.7.1911. Janike. Genealogical information. 2) p. 146: 14.9.11 'Klaas at Mr Loreny at Klippan' - Genealogical information. 3) p.170: 14.9.11. Mrs Bernarharde [?] on the Bushmen found at Bitterputs. 4) p. 172 : 15.9.11. Eyerdop. Genealogical information about Anna or =nanni and her relations. 5) p. 173: Genealogical information about Katren or !karre an and her relations - 'none of them know any stories'; names of some Bushmen 'who can sing and dance'. 6) p.174: Klaas or !kommanan !a: Genealogical information about his relations. 7) p. 178: 18.9.11. Kaiki; Stuurman'sput(?) Genealogical information about her relations. 8) p. 180: Kucharbi. 21.9.11. Information about the people who live there. 8) p. 183: Ruckseer. 21.9.11. Information about the people who live there. 9) p. 184 - 186: Kenhardt. 22.9.1. Mikki Streep gives information about the people who live there. 10) p. 187: Mikki Streep's notes on burial practices of Bushman Korannas and Kalkaffirs. 11) p. 188: Kaiki and Mikki about when Korannas came and then the Boers. '|kaggen makes the pictures'. 12) p. 189: Translation of Rachel's message; about Rachel and her relations. 13) p. 206: 24.9.11. Lukop. Information about the people who live there. 14) p. 208: Guiman's speech. 15) p. 213: 14.10.11. Zwaartputs. Katrina and Doorki: some names. 16) p.221v - 231 DBs diary 10.10.11 to 21.11.11. Includes descriptions of journey, places visited, payments (and trading) for Bushman conversation and pictures (see 221v), an excavation of Bushman woman burial, lists of clothing, searches for Bushman bones &amp; graves, photos taken, artefacts bought, reference to recording (p.226.v), language (conversation) taken down, looking for fauna, weather reports, graves dug up, skeletons, lots on burial.  17) p.232 - 234 blank. 18) p. 236: Grond [illegible] 18.11.11: Jan and Bet. The names of some of their relations. 19) p.238v - 241 feature lists of goods and food traded. 20) p. 242 Sabina. 5.12.11. 21) p. 246: 6.12.11. Dina. Names of relations and some customs including death (of child and cutting off of finger-tip). 22) p. 254: 7.12.11 Doorki. 23) p. 261: 14.10.11. Zwaartputs. 24) p.263: Names and details about some Bushmen from Rietfontein. 25) p. 264:16.10.11. Trinki or |numni - notes on her facial scarification and burn accident. 26) p. 267v: 28.10.11. Kyky or Willem:  Personal history and the giving of his name. 27) p. 268: Dina. 7.12.11. 28) p. 274: Dina and Doorki: numbers and names for things including members of the family. 29) p. 276: Doorki 8.12.11..</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/2028</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Dorothea Bleek</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Dorothea Bleek</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Dorothea Bleek notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>Dorothea Bleek - Book BC151_A3_004</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
