<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>|han=kass'o (Klein Jantje) (VIII)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-02 17:22:26.127171</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The Mantis and |kwammana go out visiting together.  The Mantis involves himself in a quarrel with a young Dasse (Hyrax), and stones fall upon him and |kwammana.  The latter, upon whom they lie loosely, is first rescued; while the Mantis owes his rescue to the entreaties of his wife, who prevails upon the people to take him out.-His teasing and troublesome ways are much blamed. (L VIII.-2. 6165-6193, and 6195.)  Another version of the story of the Crow Messengers appears, here, in connexion with the adventure related above;  |kwammana and his companion being, in this instance, those who were found by the successful bird (Corvus scapulatus). (L VIII.-2.  6147-6157) By the same narrator was also given the Rescue of |kwammana  and the Mantis, and their return home.  The Blue Crane, who is the elder sister of |kaggen, pities his sad condition.-Specimens of the peculiar manner in which the Bushman language is spoken by the wife of |kaggen, and by the Ichneumon, respectively, are here given.  (L VIII.-2. 6196-6231, 3. 6232-6236.) A note regarding the =kam-!kwe, a member of the party which went to the rescue of /kwammana and his companion (L VII.-2. 6195 rev. and 6196 rev.). |kwammana and |kaggen (the Mantis) both drink from ostrich egg-shells offered to them, |kwammana by the young bee and |kaggen by the Dassie who passes water into his shell. |kaggen curses the Dassie when he tastes its urine and the mother Dassie makes rocks roll on |kaggen and |kwammana. The people take |kaggen out from under the rocks only because his wife has asked them to. 1) |kwammana is spelt in various ways throughout the stories in which he appears, 2) p.6167v: a |xam curse referring to another person's 'part' which is 'underneath' or 'behind', 3) p. 6178v: !kaurowo calls |kaggen ||kanndoro, while other people call him |kaggen (the Mantis), 4) pp.6195v &amp; 6196v: =kum !kwe who was once a man and lived in |han=kass'o's country; he was in |kwammana's rescuing party, 5) p.6199v: the other name of the Porcupine, 6) p.6227v: the kochelman (or Agama lizard) sings, 7) p.6232v: (13 February) |xam names for and habits of animals and the doings of the Agama lizard who lies in the Driedoorn tree, including what the people say to it, 8) pp.6233v-6234v: see The !khau lizard and the rainclouds - springbok hunting follows rain and The song of the !khau lizard, 9) p.6235v: |xam names for spiders and their webs, 10) see also The Mantis and the Ticks, 11) This story is found in Books VIII-2 and VIII-3.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/610</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The Mantis and |kwammana visit the Dassie's house</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
