<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>|han=kass'o (Klein Jantje) (VIII)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-14</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The Two Lions, the Lizards, the Blue Crane, the Rhebok and the Crow. By /han=kasso (L VIII.-32. 8859-8878, 8848-8852, 19. 7643-7656). Two Lions (!gu and his companion, !haue ta =hou) kill the lizards !khau and |gi. They carry their flesh to the home of the Blue Crane and her companion, the Rhebok |ke-dde (the wives of the dead lizards), pretending to be the dead husbands. |ke-dde and the Blue Crane escape, but the Blue Crane returns home to fetch her child and is killed. The Lions find the others (|ke-dde, ||horu and |ke-dde's child), who wait for the Lions on top of a bare rock and are protected by the stones. The Black Crow draws |ke-dde up with a thong and heats stones on the ground below her house. The Black Crow throws the thong down for the Lion, and the Lion falls down onto the hot stones and dies. 1) Date on p.8864: 9 December; p.7643: 11 December 1879, 2) See also Note on the two Lions, 3) |han=kass'o heard this from his mother (|xabbi-an) and his maternal grandmother (=kammi); the |gi (lizard) is 'beautiful', 4) p.8867v: what the people say when they are thirsty, 5) p.8875v: the people's name for a python, 6) p.8877v: what people say to a companion or 'mate', 7) p.8848v: ||horu and the kochelman, 8) p.8850v: despite being people and possessing arrows, the Lions bite things rather than shoot them, 9) p.7645v: the Rhebok's name was |ke-dde when she was a person, 10) This story is found in Books VIII-19 and VIII-32.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/772</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The two Lions, the Lizards, the Blue Crane, the Rhebuck, and the Black Crow</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
