<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:contributor>The New Digital Bleek and Lloyd Archive</dc:contributor>
  <dc:creator>|han=kass'o (Klein Jantje) (VIII)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-20</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The Quagga, who was poisoned by her husband, !kuinssi/kauoken. By /han=kasso (L VIII.-29. 8603-8614, 30. 8615-8627). The Tortoise takes a piece of liver away from the baby Quagga and shares it with other animals, who agree that it tastes so good that it must be Quagga liver. They tell the young He-Dog that he must have married game and that he must kill her so that they can eat her. One of the Quagga children lets her tears fall into the cooking pots, which break. The young He-Dog marries another Quagga and the Quagga's parents hold a dance and trample the young He-Dog to death. 1) Date on p. 8615: 10 July, 2) p.8602v: |han=kass'o heard this story from his maternal grandmother (=kammi) and from his mother (|xabbi-an) when he was older; a little bird called the !kuin |kuarri, 3) p.8603v: the mother Quagga's liver must never be given to other people, 4) p.8606v: some differences between Dutch and |xam language; the |xam name of a thorny plant recognised by |han=kass'o in a picture, 5) p.8611v: (21 July 1879) a little boy who died on 20 July 1879, 6) p.8613v: on the mmain roots and the !uherriten mmain, which is another variety of the same plant, 7) p.8615opp: what the Quagga's children sang, 8) p.8615v: |han=kass'o was told about a place called !khou-|kui (or 'Neck Vulture') (but never its location), 9) p.8618v: the crying of the Quaggas, 10) p.8622v: an expression for when bad things occur, 11) This story is found in Books VIII-29 and VIII-30.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/894</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The Quagga who was poisoned by her husband, !kuin'ssi-|kauoken</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
