<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>!nanni (XI), Tamme (XII)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-06</dc:date>
  <dc:description>!nanni and Tamme contribute words and sentences relating to everyday life in their country. There is a lot of information regarding food, what plants and animals are eaten by the !kun, other groups in their country, and animals. There are fragments of songs and names and descriptions of celestial bodies, plants and animals, as well as a general vocabulary. |han=kass'o has provided various |xam words (often equivalents to the !kun words) on the verso pages. Some of the terms appear in other languages heard in !kun country, such as Makoba and Damara. 1) The first two pages (not numbered) of this notebook contain lists of clicks and notes on pronunciation, presumably in relation to the !kun (or the 'Ongova Bushmen' of Hereroland), 2) p.8977v: the name of a metal used by the Makoba in making weapons, 3) p.8981v: the |xam equivalent of the !kun word for 'child', 4) p.8983v: the !kun prepare a pot or vessel with a substance called t'e before cooking or preparing certain foods, 5) p.8987v: (11 June 1881) the porcupine is eaten by the !kun; fathers and children do not eat the =uhi, but father's fathers do, 6) p.9019v: (5 September 1881) what is said to people who understand one's language or vice versa ('a person whose thoughts are dead', 'a person who is clever or understanding'), 7) p.9033v: (8 November 1881) a note by !nanni and Tamme on respect for the quiver and the name for it used by women (particularly the wife's mother); how the women in their country are brave ('A !kun woman is a lion'), 8) p.9041v: a plant or bush (called =gua?) with a sweet-smelling flower and a description thereof; it is eaten roasted; the pod is used to make a musical instrument (called the !ne), 9) This story is found in Book XI &amp; XII-1.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/951</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd !kun notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>Words and sentences: given by !nanni and Tamme</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
