<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>|a!kunta (Stoffel) (I)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-14</dc:date>
  <dc:description>In [this] version [of the origin of death] (given by |a!kunta, and apparently unfinished) the Moon appears, at one time, to tell the little Hare that his mother will come to life again, and that, therefore, he need not cry;  but the little Hare does not believe, and continues to cry, saying that the Moon is deceiving him. The Moon upon this becomes angry, and threatens to beat his mouth. Towards the end of the story, there is some Moon and Hare language, with its peculiar click; and also some remarks upon the mode of pronouncing it. (B XV. 1403-1482) The Moon tells the little Hare to stop crying over his mother's death as she will come back to life the next day. The Moon tells the story of the resurrection of the He-Ostrich and of the new Moon after it was stabbed by the Sun. He also talks of the death of animals and people (those who dwell on the earth) as well as the speech of different animals, people and the Moon. The little Hare contradicts the Moon who tells him he is foolish. The little Hare tells the Moon that he tells the stories his mother has taught him. The Moon says he is the only one who understands, because he is the Moon, and speaks nicely whereas all others speak their own languages. (This story includes a section called The Moon's speech: pp.1469-1482) 1) p.1468v: notes on clicks, including the one made by the Moon, 2) p.1470v: the Anteater, the Hare and the Moon all speak in an 'ugly manner', 3) This story is found in Book XV.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/66</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Wilhelm Bleek</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Wilhelm Bleek</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Wilhelm Bleek notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>Moon and little Hare (includes: The Moon's speech)</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
