<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>|k'abe</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>||hauku</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>O=k||n</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bekiman</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Baraxas</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>|kam ||ari</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Abraham</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kati. |kanaku or |hanaku</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>!urike</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-01</dc:date>
  <dc:description>Notes on |auni, Vol.1, made at Frankenwald Research Station, Witwatersrand University. Words and sentences and much personal history. Also some fragmented information about artefacts, ornaments and daily life, markings (cuts made for hunting and the cutting of girls for example). 1) Written on opposite page of inside front cover: '|auni I'. 2) p.422: Frankenwald 10.10.1936. I |k'abe, nephew of Tutai. Words and sentences with some given by 'other |auni couple'. 3) p.424: 11.10.36. |hanaku. Words and sentences. 4) p.428v ('429r.'): 12.10.36. Words and sentences including the cutting off of fingers to cure illness (429v) and other fragments of description. 5) p.430: 13.10.36. Words and sentences including fragments of personal history (death of 'Scotty's' relations due to fever, another's died due to smallpox, marriages and names) as well as some history of the inhabitants of the immediate area such as working relations, languages spoken, a girl cut at her 'girl's initiation' by the aunts. Girls that get cut (not the =komani for instance), where the |auni live in relation to other groups, names of people in Tutai's (and this individual's) family. 6) p.439 &amp; opp. page - 440: 14.10.36. =komani. Piet or ||hauku, names of others and some of their personal history. |auni.  ||kabe and his family, their names, some of their personal history - how they learnt to speak Hottentot, their relations with others: 'later came the Bastaards and now the Boers are coming'. 7) p.441. Names for relations. 8) p.442: A ball game played by girls of a certain age, ornaments and face powders, decoration used by girls. Personal history, marriages, names of relations. 9) p.445: words and sentences mostly weapons and following springbok spoor. 10) p.447: 16.10.36. Words and sentences including names of relations, ornaments and dress. There are references to a photograph with names and information about the informants pictured (Abraham, |kum ke, Miki for instance) (p.449). 11) p.452: O=k||n. Bekiman, Baraxas. Words and sentences. 12) p.453: 17.10.36. !urike. Names of relations, personal history along with words and sentences. 13) p.459: 18.10.36. Kati. |kanaku. Words and sentences, fragments of personal history, names of relations, mention of the 'missus' and how 'I have not stories to tell'. 14) p.465: 19.10.36. Words and sentences mostly relating to landscape and fauna of the area, ostrich and kudu. Personal history of Txsbaku [?] who married a 'Vaalpens' and afterwards married Abraham. 15) p.467: 20.10.36. ||ka'be &amp; |kam ||ari. Words and sentences..</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/2053</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Dorothea Bleek notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>Dorothea Bleek - Book BC151_A3_029</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
