<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>Dia!kwain (David Hoesar) (V)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-12</dc:date>
  <dc:description>Versions of this transformation [of 'new maidens'] into frogs, ascribed chiefly to a new Maidens acts of disobedience, are given in the Katkop dialect by !kweiten ta //ken (L VI.-1. 3930-3958), and by Dia!kwain. (B XXVII. 2609-2618, continued in L V.-2. 3864-3881). When a girl becomes a new maiden she must not look at people or else she will transfix them. This is what happened to the young man long ago when the new maiden looked at him after she had gone to hear him play his !goura. That is why the new maidens have to lie in a house made for them by the old women so they cannot look or laugh at anyone. The old women take care of them. A maiden disobeys her mother and leaves the house to go wash herself in the spring. As a result she and her people are taken away by the Rain and transformed into frogs. 1) This story is continued in Lloyd's book, vol.2, pp.3864-3881, 2) This story features notes and elaborations on Dia!kwain's (David Hoesar) narrative (for example p.2609v) by !kweiten ta ||ken who came to Mowbray in June 1874 and was Dia!kwain's sister (and =kasin's wife), 3) A note made on 24 October 1874 by Lloyd (told by !kweiten ta ||ken) tells of how old women order the maidens to remain in the house they have made for them (see p.2611v), 4) This story is found in Book XXVII.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/126</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Wilhelm Bleek</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Wilhelm Bleek</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Wilhelm Bleek notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>About new maidens</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
