<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>||kabbo (Jantje) (II)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-12</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The Rain-maker is asked to milk a nice female Rain which is gentle, the rain-clouds being her hair (L II.-24. 2213-2226, 25. 2227-2263). The verso pages of the account contain further notes as to the actions of the rain and the rainmaker, as well as mentioning the rain's legs (or rain-water) and ribs (or rain-clouds) and how the rainmaker rides the rain-cow. 1) Note on the inside of the front cover (Book II-24) that parts of the story were translated in 1913 &amp; 1914, 2) Note on the inside of the front cover (Book II-25) that some parts of the story were translated in 1899, 3) Date on p.2227: 2 December; p.2258: 11 December, 4) Note on contents page (Book II-25): '||kabbo read over with LL [Lucy Lloyd] in Oct '73 and said story was finished', 5) p.2231v: a note that what |han=kass'o (Klein Jantje) says in January 1878 is a little different to ||kabbo's words, 6) p.2239v: the name of the high mountain (kamm xhara ka !kau) at Wittberg where rain is made; it isn't in Bushmanland and '... Jantje has not seen it, but Stoffel has - Kafirs live at the water near it.', 7) p.2254v: ||kabbo's mother told him that the rain-man broke one of the rain's ribs and threw the pieces to different places; the ribs were a 'long dark thick cloud', 8) p.2257v: the name for autumn, which occurs at the end of February and the beginning of March in Bushmanland, 9) p.2261v: a note by ||kabbo on the colour of springbok hair at different times, 10) See also Rainmaking: another story of it, 12) This story is found in Books II-24 and II-25.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/274</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publishers>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publishers>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The story of the old man who makes rain</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
