<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>Dia!kwain (David Hoesar) (V)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-11</dc:date>
  <dc:description>Death. The stars know the time at which a Bushman dies, and the fall of one announces, to those who are not aware of it, that something bad has happened.  When, after this, a 'Hammerkop' (Scopus umbretta), flies, calling out over the Bushmen, the people know that someone belonging to them has died. Girls who have been killed by lightning are changed into stars. Girls who have been taken away by the water become like a beautiful water-flower, which will not allow itself to be plucked, and disappears when approached. Such flowers must be let alone. The place in the sky in which lightning appears should be looked at, so that the lightning may not kill us by stealth. In the Katkop dialect, by Dia!kwain (L V.-22. 5776-5809). 1) p.5776v: when a person dies the heart falls over like something which has been standing upright that then falls to one side, 2) p.5779v: the Hamerkop, called by Dutch farmers the Hammer-bir-kop, Latin name Scopus umbretta, |xam name !hin; the |xam name for its cry, which it repeats twice, 3) pp.5794v &amp; 5795v: what Dia!kwain's mother's (=kamme-an) mother (|abbe-ttu) told her about the flowers growing at the water's edge, 4) See also Falling stars, 5) This story is found in Book V-22.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/531</dc:identifier>
  <dc:publisher>Lucy Lloyd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:source>Lucy Lloyd</dc:source>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>Stars and death</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
