<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creators>||kabbo (Jantje) (II)</dc:creators>
  <dc:date>2020-09-06</dc:date>
  <dc:description>||kabbo's account of how he was taken by black men from the place where he was eating springbok, and was bound, along with some of his relations. They were taken to the magistrate, and after speaking to him and presumably sentenced they were put into stocks in the jail. Korannas were also imprisoned in this manner. They were all fed sheep. They were then taken to Victoria where they had to roll stones and fill small wagons with earth. They were then taken to Beaufort jail, where they were given tobacco to smoke. After this they were chained and taken to the Breakwater Convict Station where they were to work. A white man took them to the train at night, and early in the morning they were taken to the Cape. Here they fell asleep at noon. There are two endings to this narrative, one given by ||kabbo at a later date when the narrative was read back to him (see p.248v). The second embellished ending features the 'fire wagon' or train. //kabbos Capture and Journey to Cape Town are twice described by him. One of these accounts (L II.-1. 266-272), the beginning of which is also given in another version (B II. 350), carries him only a part of the way; while the other narrates the whole journey down, as far as the Breakwater (L II.-1. 242-250). 1) Some of the verso page notes and corrections were made by |a!kunta, 2) Note on the inside of the back cover of this notebook: 'Finished correcting Sept 15/71 from Jantje Toorm himself', 3) p.245v: Note on the wagon of the narrative - something like a barrow, but requiring many people to carry it, 4) p.246v: This wagon is called a bori, 5) See also //kabbo's account of being caught and jailed (2nd version) and Jantje's capture and Jantje in the train, 6) This story is found in Book II-1.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/166</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>||kabbo's account of being caught and brought to the Breakwater</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
