<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:creator>|han=kass'o (Klein Jantje) (VIII)</dc:creator>
  <dc:date>2020-09-02</dc:date>
  <dc:description>The Anteater, the young Springbok, the Lynx, and the Partridge, by lhan=kasso (L VIII.-29. 8561-8602). An Anteater (a person of the Early Race) steals a female Springbok child and disappears into her hole. The Lynx tells the young Springbok (named !khoukau) that the Anteater is not her real mother and they leave together, but the Partridge sees them and tells the Anteater. The Anteater follows after the two, under the ground, popping her head up sometimes to see where they are. The Lynx makes a loop with his bowstring and throws it around the neck of the Anteater, pulling her from the ground. The Anteater curses the Lynx, saying that he shall be a Lynx and go about by night. The Lynx curses the Anteater, saying that she shall be an anteater by night. 1) p.8560v: |han=kass'o heard this story from his mother (|xabbi-an), his maternal grandmother (=kammi), and his step-grandmother (Tuai-an); see The song of the Springbok mothers, 2) p.8568v: a kaross in which children are carried:, 3) p.8571v: on the 'Bushmen's cursing', 4) p.8576v: a |xam term for conspiracy (or intrigue), 5) p.8584v: another name for a man called Jacob Bastard; see An eruptive illness called !hamman-xu, 6) pp.8585v-8586v: see Avoiding where the jackal or the hyena have passed water, 7) p.8601v: the Crieboom, or ||kana tree, and the Doornboom, or !khou tree, 8) See also The Anteater's story or The Anteater, Springbok, Lynx and Partridge, 9) This story is found in Book VIII-29.</dc:description>
  <dc:format>Unqualified Dublin Core</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://pumbaa.cs.uct.ac.za/~balnew/metadata/stories/892</dc:identifier>
  <dc:rights>CC-BY-NC-ND</dc:rights>
  <dc:subject>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</dc:subject>
  <dc:title>The Anteater, the young Springbok, the Lynx and the Partridge</dc:title>
  <dc:type>story</dc:type>
</oai_dc:dc>
