<item type="story"><id>828</id>
<collection>Lucy Lloyd |xam notebooks</collection>
<title>The lion has the power of turning itself into other things</title>
<summary><i>The Lion is believed to possess the power of assuming other forms. (L VIII.-23. 8075-8077).</i> It assumes the form of a hartebeest because it wants the people to try and head it as if it were game. It also assumes the form of a person (and wears a kaross). </summary><comments>1) p.8074v: |han≠kass&apos;o heard this from Tsatsi as well as from a man called !kui (or Ttarro-hho, or Bartman Bastard); this latter man&apos;s youthful name was Ttarro-hho and his grown-up name was !kui !ka xu, which he was given because he was a &apos;bad man&apos; and a woman threw fire at him, burning him, when he &apos;wished to marry her&apos;; a lion who &apos;does not understand&apos; comes to people&apos;s huts to kill them, 2) pp.8075v &amp; 8076v: (28 December 1878) see <i>Children do not say the lion&apos;s name at night</i>, 3) See also <i>A wild cat, when many have been killed by a person changes itself into a lion and kills the slayer</i>, 4) This story is found in Book VIII-23</comments><date>22 December 1878 (started)</date><storypages>8075-8077</storypages><category>Transformation</category><author>|han≠kass'o (Klein Jantje) (VIII)</author><keyword><kw>lion</kw><subkw>its actions and habits</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>lion</kw><subkw>&apos;terror kills us&apos;</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>lion</kw><subkw>has the power of turning itself into other things</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>lion</kw><subkw>can transform itself</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>lion</kw><subkw>has magic powers</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>lion</kw><subkw>people lie in wait for it in its hartebeest-form</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>lion</kw><subkw>becomes a hartebeest to trick people</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>lion</kw><subkw>deceives so it can kill people</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>lion</kw><subkw>is cunning</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>lion</kw><subkw>assumes the form of a person in a kaross</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>transformation</kw><subkw>the lion has the power of turning itself into other things</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>transformation</kw><subkw>lion becomes a person</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>transformation</kw><subkw>lion becomes a hartebeest</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>transformation</kw><subkw>lion wears a kaross</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>hartebeest</kw><subkw>the lion wants the people to try and head it</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>hartebeest</kw><subkw>the lion tricks people in its form</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>hartebeest</kw><subkw>lion has the power of turning itself into</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>kaross</kw><subkw>the lion assumes the form of a person and wears one</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>kaross</kw><subkw>lion has the power of turning itself into other things</subkw></keyword>
<keyword><kw>magic power</kw><subkw>of the lion which can turn itself into other things</subkw></keyword>

<page><file>A2_1_98_08075.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_098</book></page>
<page><file>A2_1_98_08076.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_098</book></page>
<page><file>A2_1_98_08077.JPG</file><book>BC_151_A2_1_098</book></page>
</item>
